Guide to the Radio Haiti Papers, circa 1934-2003, bulk 1968-2003 RL.11499
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Radio Haiti-Inter, 1972-2003
  - Press, 1972-1995
    - M. Montas interviews J.L. Dominique, 1972; 1 folder (Box 168)
      Interview of Jean Dominique by Michèle Montas, published in Le Nouvelliste on 22 November 1972.
    - Petit Samedi Soir, 1977-1980; 2 folders (Box 168)
      Complete and partial issues of Le Petit Samedi Soir about Radio Haiti and Jean Dominique, including the October 1980 arrest of Konpè Filo.
  - Programming and business, 1980-2003
    - Editorial, Michèle Montas, 2003-02-21; 1 folder (Box 168)
      Text of Michèle Montas's final editorial, announcing the closure of Radio Haiti.
    - Face à l'Opinion, 1996-1999; 1 folder (Box 168)
      Introductions to and notes on Jean Dominique's daily Face à l'Opinion interviews.
    - Inter-Actualités (1-3), 1986-1987; 1998-2003; 3 folders (Box 168)
      Handwritten schedules and detailed descriptions of Radio Haiti's daily programming. Folders arranged by year.
    - Inter-Actualités (4-10), 1986-1987; 1998-2003; 7 folders (Box 169)
    - Inter-Actualités (11-19), 1986-1987; 1998-2003; 9 folders (Box 170)
    - Inter-Actualités (20-23), 1986-1987; 1998-2003; 4 folders (Box 171)
    - Life of a radio station, 1977-2000 (Box 171)
      Schedules of Radio Haiti programming, notes on pogramming, internal memos to the newsroom, information regarding fees for sponsors and advertisers, correpondence. Also includes the birth certificate (1955) of one Dieu-Puissant Charles -- ordinary people would often come to Radio Haiti as a sort of communal "lost and found."
    - Misc. correspondence, 1976-1996, undated (Box 171)
      Letter from attorney Osner Fevry to Jean Dominique from January 1980, apologizing for having wrongly claimed that Dominique was present at an event on 27 December 1979; undated Christmas card (perhaps 1989). 1987 letter to the direction of Radio Haiti about an abandoned child; communication from ZANTRAY; Uruguayan journalist Sergio Lago; letter from Ozzie Leonard of WNYE; and others.
    - Spots and jingles, 1989-2001, undated; 1 folder (Box 171)
      Scripts for Radio Haiti's spots and jingles. Includes drafts of "On a tout essayé," the Entre Nous intro, "Kinan'm," jazz program intro ("Des rivages de Gorée..."), "Soti Coq Chante rive Rossignol...", Justice for Jean Dominiquespots ("Lò yo sasinen Dr Ary Bordes"), and others.
    - Banner: Radio Haïti, 1330 am, L'écoute intelligente (Box 192)
      One red-and-blue banner of Mylar-type material measuring 87 x 29 inches: "Radio Haïti, 1330 am, l'écoute intelligente." Undated.
    - Rubber stamps (Box 193)
      Two rubber stamps, both undated. One says "Radio Haïti-Inter" and features the station's trademark vèvè symbol, as designed by Rose-Marie Desruisseau. The other says "Radio Haiti" in art deco font and has the call signs 4vw, 4vhw, and 4vrw.
  - Reporting, 1978, 1999
    - 1978 elections, Dominican Republic, 1 folder (Box 171)
      Reactions and contestations after Radio Haiti's reporting on the May 1978 elections in the Dominican Republic, and the Agence France Presse's dispatch based on Radio Haiti's reporting. Radio Haiti reported rumors that there had been a coup d'état, but did not report that there was in fact a coup d'état; AFP reported that there had been a coup d'état. Radio Haiti responds to the allegations.
    - Tribute to Radio Haiti, planters in Léogâne, 1999 (Box 171)
      Radio Haiti report on a tribute to the station by sugar planters in Léogâne, who honored Radio Haiti for their support in the struggle against counterfeit clairin.
  - Repression, 1977-2001
    - April 1989 attack, 1 folder (Box 171)
      Press about and support for Radio Haiti following the military's 6 April 1989 attack on Radio Haiti. Includes an inventory of the damage, Jean Dominique's correspondence with Alfred Mentor (Director General of the Ministry of Information), statements of solidarity from Tèt Kole Ti Peyizan Ayisyen, the Soeurs de Sainte Anne, the Committee to Protect Journalists, Jeunesse Ouvrière Chrétienne, Léon Manus, TKL Saint Joseph, Mouvman Peyizan Papay, CATH labor union, LAPPH, Fritz Lebon, and others. Also includes Jean Dominique's statement of thanks for those who expressed solidarity, and two issues of Balance magazine from March 1989, on the repression leading up to the attack.
    - Exile and return, 1980-1986, 1981-1986; 2 folders (Box 171)
      See also: November 28, 1980 crackdown; Repression of independent media
      Materials related to the 1980 exile of Radio Haiti journalists, their return in 1986, and the solidarity campaign to relaunch Radio Haiti in 1986. Includes reporting on the return of Jean Dominique and Michèle Montas, Liliane Pierre-Paul, Konpè Filo, as well as non-Radio Haiti journalists such as Pierre Clitandre and Jean-Robert Hérard. Also includes several issues of Le Petit Samedi Soir about the "November 28 exiles." Also contains Jean Dominique's 1981 letter to Luis Teofilo Nuñez Arismendi of the Inter-American Press Association (SIP), thanking him and Venezuela for their support.
    - Jean-Robert Delciné, 2001; 1 folder (Box 171)
      See also: Violence against journalists
      Radio Haiti materials related to the 2001 attack on Radio Haiti journalist Jean-Robert Delciné by police in Cité Soleil. Includes Radio Haiti reporting, letter from Commissaire de Gouvernement Josué Pierre-Louis from J.J. Dominique and Michèle Montas.
    - Violence against journalists, 1990-1991; 1 folder (Box 172)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to violence against Radio Haiti journalists, particularly aggression against Fritzson Orius, Hughes Florvil, and Tony Vernio. Vernio was abused by justice of the peace Tulien Vincent in Port-de-Paix.
    - Widmaïer-Radio Haiti affair, 1977-1981; 3 folders (Box 172)
      Materials related to the 1977-1979 lawsuit against Radio Haiti by Duvalierist attorney Constantin Mayard-Paul on behalf of the widow of Ricardo Widmaïer. Includes newspapers (Jeune Presse, Haïti-Hebdo, Le Nouveau Monde, Le Nouvelliste, Le Matin, Manchèt, Panorama, Haïti Observateur), a handwritten letter of support from "Marie Thérèse" to Jean Dominique, an open letter from "Un groupe de patriotes et de démocrates" in New York.
    - Shell casing (Box 193)
      One used shell casing from a bullet. Undated. Radio Haiti staff kept a jar of bullets fired at the station. This shell was found in one of the reel-to-reel boxes.
    - Raffle ticket for paintings, 1979 (Box 172)
      By 1979, Radio Haiti had lost many of their sponsors, who were afraid of being associated with a radio station that was openly critical of the Duvalier government. In December 1979, Radio Haiti held a raffle to raise money for the station, featuring paintings by Haitian painters Valcin II, Dieudonné Cédor, Emmanuel Pierre-Charles, Casimir Joseph, G. Hector, Rose-Marie Desruisseau, Manes Descollines, Wilfrid Louis, Jocelyn Joseph, Arijac, Monfort Laguerre, and Jean Nasalio Maxi. This raffle ticket was found in the tape box for RL10059RR1538, and was apparently later used as scratch paper.
  - Research materials, 1988; 1991
    - Le Moniteur (1-4), 1988; 1991; 4 folders (Box 172)
      Full editions of the official government newspaper Le Moniteur from 1988 (presidencies of Henri Namphy, Leslie Manigat, and Prosper Avril) and 1991 (Jean-Bertrand Aristide's first presidency and the first four months of the military junta that overthrew Aristide on 30 September 1991). Folders arranged by year.
    - Le Moniteur (5-8), 1988; 1991; 4 folders (Box 173)
  - Station equipment
    - Marantz PMD-0201 field recorder, early 1980s (Box Equipment 001)
      Radio Haiti journalist Pierre Emmanuel explains, "This was Michèle's machine. No one was allowed to touch it without special permission. It was a Marantz, but its nickname was 'Prunelle' which means "apple of my eye." She came back from exile in the United States with it [in 1986]."
    - RCA Type 77-D microphone, early 1950s (Box Equipment 002)
      This microphone first belonged to the original Radio Haiti, before Jean Dominique bought the lease in the early 1970s. It was damaged beyond repair on November 28, 1980, when Duvalier's forces destroyed the station on Rue du Quai. When Duvalier fell in 1986 and Radio Haiti returned from exile, they moved to Delmas and brought this microphone with them so they would never forget what had happened. It was crushed in the January 2010 earthquake, which damaged the Radio Haiti building so badly that it had to be torn down.
    - Arrakis 500-SC broadcast console, circa 1980 (Box Equipment 003)
      Broadcast console/mixer, made in Loveland, Colorado, featured in the opening scenes of Jonathan Demme's The Agronomist.
- Rule of Law, 1972-2003
  - Constitution, 1986-2001
    - Avant-Projet de Constitution, 1986; 1 folder (Box 174)
      1986 draft of the Constitution.
    - Civil Society Organizations, 1988-1990; 1 folder (Box 174)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to civil society organizations' responses to and actions around the Constitution and its implementation. Primarily the Komite Tèt Ansanm pou Onè Respè Konstitisyon-an.
    - Commemorations, amendments, 1990-2001; 1 folder (Box 174)
      Radio Haiti materials about commemorations of 29 March 1987 referendum, the 1987 Constitution and the 1801 Constitution and amendments to the Constitution. Speech by Florence Elie on the prize for the student competition on the theme of the Constitition. Text by Evens Paul of the Konvansyon Inite Demokratik (KID), "La Constitution dans l'Impasse." Also includes a Creole translation of the national anthem.
    - Constituent Assembly, 1986; 3 folders (Box 174)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the constituent assembly and creation of the 1987 Constitution. External materials include external press; open letters and petitions from grassroots groups, civil society organizations, political parties, and individuals; press releases and information from the Haitian government (mainly the Ministry of Information and Communication). Includes debates and concerns around Creole as the national language, the Conseil National de Gouvernement (CNG), and other topics relating to the creation of the Constitution.
    - Constituent Assembly (1-2 of 4), 1987; 2 folders (Box 174)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the constituent assembly and creation of the 1987 Constitution. External materials include external press; open letters and petitions from grassroots groups, civil society organizations, political parties, and individuals; press releases and information from the Haitian government (mainly the Ministry of Information and Communication), CNG decrees. Includes debates and concerns around agrarian reform, the army and police, public administration, recognition of Vodou, and other issues relating to the creation of the Constitution.
    - Constituent Assembly (3-4 of 4), 1987; 2 folders (Box 175)
    - General, 1987; 1 folder (Box 175)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the creation and implementation of the 1987 Constitution, especially grassroots groups, civil society organizations and the democratic movement's perspectives on the creation of the Constitution and the immediate aftermath of the March 29 referendum. Includes the Chrétiens Sociaux Démocrates, Mouvement d'Action Démocratique (MAD), Mobilisation pour le Développement National (MDN), Lafontant Joseph, among others. Also includes anonymous ypewritten document containing suggestions on the separation of powers (executive, legislative, judiciary).
    - General, 1988-1989; 1 folder (Box 175)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to implementation of and respect for the 1987 Constitution. Includes material from the Komite Tèt Ansanm pou Onè Respè Konstitisyon-an, Tèt Kole Ti Peyizan Ayisyen, and other grassroots and civil society groups, CATH-CLAT labor union, Parti Démocrate Chrétien Haïtien (PDCH), MDN, a text by Edouard Tardieu, text by Yves Volel of the Rassemblement des démocrates chrétiens (RDC) with one page missing, decree by Prosper Avril, among other resources.
    - March 29, 1987 referendum (1-3 of 4), 3 folders (Box 175)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the March 29, 1987 referendum on the constitution. External materials include external press; open letters and petitions from several grassroots groups, civil society organizations, political parties, and individuals; press releases and information from the Haitian government (mainly the Ministry of Information and Communication), materials from the International Center on Development Policy (US think tank), promotional material and political propaganda, CNG decrees. Also includes Radio Haiti's daily news ("interactualités") from around the country, primarily relating to the lead-up to the March 29 constitutional referendum, but occasionally including other daily miscellany. Also includes Radio Haiti materials (scripts and notes) and external materials (external press, communiqués from grassroots organizations and civil society organizations) relating to the results of the March 29, 1987 referendum on the Constitution.
    - March 29, 1987 referendum (4 of 4), 1 folder (Box 176)
    - Text - Constitution, 1986-1987; 1 folder (Box 176)
      Text of the 1987 Constitution (in several forms) including articles voted on in 1986.
  - Justice, 1977-2003
    - Commission Justice et Paix, 1989-2002; 4 folders (Box 176)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the reports and activities of the Commission Justice et Paix (Commission Episcopale Justice et Paix, Commission Episcopale Nationale Justice et Paix).
    - Commission nationale de vérité et de justice, 1994-1996; 1 folder (Box 176)
      See also: Raboteau massacre
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the Commission nationale de vérité et de justice (CNVJ) under Françoise Boucard, including investigation into the Raboteau massacre and other human rights violations during the coup years.
    - Cour de Cassation, 2000-2001; 1 folder (Box 176)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the Cour de Cassation, including nominations and deaths of judges.
    - Cour des Comptes, 1996-2002; 2 folders (Box 176)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the Cour des Comptes (Cour supérieure des comptes et du contentieux administratif, CSCCA), including Gilbert Mythil's false credentials and accusations bu Jean-Robert Sabala, the "Mains Propres" anti-corruption campaign, mismanagement of Téléco, and other topics.
    - Fundación Arias para la Paz y el Progreso Humano, 1995; 1 folder (Box 183)
      External materials from the 1995 Fundación Arias para la Paz y el Progreso Humano international conference in Costa Rica and Panama.
    - Justice system, 1977-1979; 1 folder (Box 177)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to legal matters in the late 1970s, including the Jean Dominique v. Widmaïer case (in which the latter was represented by Constantin Mayard Paul), Ernst Trouillot, and the 29 March 1979 decree.
    - Justice system, 1986; 1 folder (Box 177)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the creation of tribunals and to judicial cases, including the trial of Luc Désir. Includes communication from Lafontant Joseph.
    - Justice system, 1987; 2 folders (Box 177)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the creation of tribunals, judicial reform, the head of the bar association Ernst Mallebranche, and the cases of Luc Désir and Valcius Estinval, among other cases.
    - Justice system, 1988; 3 folders (Box 177)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to tribunals, court proceedings. Includes the cases of Jean Camille Musac, Jocelyn Beauchard, Paul Vericain; Eddy Moïse; assassination of Yves Volel; aftermath of the 29 November 1987 Ruelle Vaillant massacre; public prosecutor Mireille Pluviose; among other topics.
    - Justice system, 1989; 1 folder (Box 177)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to judicial reform, tribunals and court proceedings, including the "tribunal populaire" at Côtes-de-Fer and other grassroots justice efforts; and other topics.
    - Justice system, 1990; 1 folder (Box 177)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to tribunals and court proceedings, including the case of Marc Antoine Lacroix, the death of Roseline Vaval, the aftermath of the 1988 St. Jean Bosco massacre and trial of Elysée Jean François, and other cases.
    - Justice system, 1991; 3 folders (Box 177)
      Radio Haiti materials related to judicial reform, tribunals and court proceedings, including the case of Marc Antoine Lacroix, Isidore Pongnon, peasant declarations against chefs de section and former macoutes, the arrest of Nicol Poitevien in connection with the 1987 Jean Rabel massacre, the arrest of Ertha Pascal Trouillot, former political prisoners' accusations against Prosper Avril, and other topics. Also includes report on arrest warrants for Williams Régala (implicated in the 1964 Jérémie Vespers massacre and the 29 November 1987 election violence), former Duvalierists, landowners implicated in the Gervais massacre, and landowners implicated in the Jean Rabel massacre.
    - Justice system, 1995; 4 folders (Box 178)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the justice system, judicial reform, court cases and tribunals in the aftermath of the coup years. Includes justice for victims of the coup d'état and FRAPH, including the aftermath of the Raboteau massacre; the Commission nationale de vérité et de justice (CNVJ); the Commission Justice et Paix; Ministry of Justice; presidential decrees (Aristide); Schiller Mathieu; the arrest of Jean Tatoune; grassroots groups including the Mouvman Peyizan Papay (MPP) and Fondation Jean-Marie Vincent; Joël Khawly; Jean Danton Léger; and other materials and topics. Also includes the second part of Radio Haiti's overview (bilan) of justice in 1995.
    - Justice system (1-3 of 5), 1996; 3 folders (Box 178)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the justice system, judicial reform, court cases and tribunals. Includes the Guy Malary case; charges against Claude Raymond; the aftermath of the coup years and FRAPH; the aftermath of the Raboteau massacre; Jean Danton Leger; human rights organizations; Mission Civile Internationale en Haïti (MICIVIH) and other international cooperation and efforts; the Commission Justice et Paix; the Commission nationale de vérité et de justice (CNVJ); Ministry of Justice; presidential decrees (Préval); construction of tribunals; judicial training; criminal courts; and other materials and topics.
    - Justice system (4-5 of 5), 1996; 2 folders (Box 179)
    - Justice system, 1997; 6 folders (Box 179)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the justice system, judicial reform, court cases and tribunals. Includes criminal cases; the aftermath of the Raboteau massacre, including Castera Cenafils; ex-FADH; the Ministry of Justice, the Commission Justice et Paix; Osner Fevry; international cooperation and aid in judicial matters.
    - Justice system, 1998; 5 folders (Box 180)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the justice system, judicial reform, court cases, and tribunals. Includes human rights organizations (including Fondation 30 Septembre, NCHR and POHDH), international efforts and cooperation including MICIVIH, the École de la Magistrature, criminal courts, Ministry of Justice, Luckner Pierre, police authority and police violence, ongoing justice efforts against leaders of the 1991 coup d'état, and other topics.
    - Justice system (1-4 of 5), 1999; 4 folders (Box 180)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the justice system, court cases, and tribunals. Includes criminal courts; MICIVIH and other forms of international cooperation; justice for victims of the coup d'état and FRAPH (including the Raboteau massacre); the Police Nationale d'Haïti (PNH) under Pierre Denizé; the assassination of ex-colonel Jean Lamy; Adolfo Pérez Esquivel; the arrest of Jean Coles Rameau; grassroots human rights organizations including Fondation 30 Septembre and POHDH; the Carrefour-Feuilles massacre; justice for the victims and commemorations of the St. Jean Bosco massacre, the Ruelle Vaillant massacre, and the Jean Rabel massacre.
    - Justice system (5 of 5), 1999; 1 folder (Box 181)
    - Justice system, 2000; 3 folders (Box 181)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the justice system, court cases, and tribunals. Includes criminal courts; the Jean Dominique and Jean-Claude Louissaint assassinations; general impunity and calls for justice from international organizations, including Amnesty International and the National Coalition for Haitian Rights (NCHR); MICIVIH; justice for victims of the coup d'état, including Raboteau; open letters from Sen. Irvelt Chéry; post-election violence in Anse d'Hainault.
    - Justice system, 2001; 4 folders (Box 181)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the justice system, tribunals and court proceedings, including the Carrefour-Feuilles massacre, the Fort Mercredi massacre, the Jean Dominique case and judge Claudy Gassant, Dongot Joseph, Gabriel Fortuné, Marjorie Rivette, Jean Sénat Fleury, Dr. Blondel Auguste, charges against former FADH, Paul Raymond and the Parti Populaire National (PPN), juvenile justice, criminal courts, investigation into the assassination of Yvon Toussaint, the PNH under Piere Denizé, among other topics.
    - Justice system, 2002-2003; 4 folders (Box 182)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the justice system, justice reform, tribunals, and court proceedings. Includes criminal courts; impunity (including the Piatre massacre and the Brignol Lindor assassination); the Jean Dominique case and judge Claudy Gassant; the Association Nationale des Magistrats Haïtiens (ANAMAH); human rights organizations including NCHR; insecurity and the PNH; the Commission Justice et Paix; Ministry of Justice; and the Forum Citoyen pour la Réforme de la Justice, among other topics.
    - Justice system, undated; 1 folder (Box 182)
      Undated external materials related to the justice system, including Pwogram Refòm Jidisyè pamphlet by the Ministry of Justice (likely mid-1990s), essay by Jean-André Rousseau "Pour le prestige et le renom de la justice haïtienne", POHDH statement on impunity.
    - Ministère de la Justice, 1986-1990; 2 folders (Box 182)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the Ministry of Justice under François Saint-Fleur François Latortue, Gilbert Austin, and Augustin Romain Cème, including efforts to remove and prosecute Duvalierist judges and deputies.
    - Ministère de la Justice, 1996-1997; 2 folders (Box 182)
      Bilan of Ministry of Justice 1996-1997. République d'Haïti Ministère de la Justice et de la Sécurité Publique: Élements d'orientation pour une réforme de la Justice en Haïti.
    - Office de la Protection du Citoyen, 1997-2002; 1 folder (Box 183)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the Office de la Protection du Citoyen, under Louis E. Roy and Florence Elie, including activities and human rights considerations.
    - Security, prison, human rights, 1999; 1 folder (Box 183)
      See also: Ensekirite; Police; Human Rights